The Python course in the IT Specialist series
introduces one to Python, a very versatile and
popular programming language, and maps to
the IT Specialist-Python exam. The course
will introduce you to the basics of Python and
some of its uses and will go through the exam
objectives from start to finish. To help put a
little real-world application into this course,
many of the code examples you will see will be
snippets of game development, one of the many uses
for Python. You will learn about other uses in the
next topic, What is Python? This course consists
of the videos you are watching, practice labs,
pre- and post-assessment tests for each domain,
and a project workbook with exercises geared
toward helping you solidify what you will
learn in these videos. There are six domains
in this IT Specialist Python exam. They are:
Operations using Data Types and Operators
Flow Control with Decisions and Loops
Input and Output Operations
Code Documentation and Structure
Troubleshooting and Error Handling
Operations using Modules and Tools
For the exam, ensure you obtain a copy of the
objectives, as shown here, and I would download
a copy as I have done here as the website version
is hard to read. Pay close attention to the first
words you see in each second group of objectives,
as those words play into the types of questions
you can expect on the exam. For example, when you
see construct and analyze, be ready to determine
the code needed to reach a specified outcome
and be able to take an existing piece of code
and answer questions about what the code does.
Don’t worry. We will show you some examples of
analyzing code as we cover these topics. Also,
if you have not yet done so, I would suggest
taking the 90-minute Introduction to Programming
course or having an equivalent level of knowledge
before tackling this course. The Introduction
to Programming course covers basic concepts,
such as properties, methods, variables, and loops,
without emphasizing any language. If you already
have that knowledge, great. If not, we will still
review some basic concepts in this Python course,
but the Introduction to Programming course
will help you learn Python or any other
programming language. Finally, get some
hands-on practice. Build small blocks of
code that produce a result. In the topic after
next, we will show you what you need to install
to start learning and creating using Python.
Let’s move on now and get an introduction to
Python and examine what differentiates
it from other programming languages.